<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the brethren who are for the established government and judicatories of this church, expressing their earnest desires of union and peace with their dissenting brethen.</title>
            <author>Wood, James, 1608-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3397</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18219785</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18219785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107207</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107207)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1138:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the brethren who are for the established government and judicatories of this church, expressing their earnest desires of union and peace with their dissenting brethen.</title>
                  <author>Wood, James, 1608-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Wood by Wing and Halkett and Laing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Scotland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107207:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE BRETHREN, who are for the eſtabliſhed GOVERNMENT and JUDICATORIES OF THIS CHURCH, Expreſsing their earneſt deſires of UNION and PEACE with their DISSENTING BRETHREN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:107207:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107207:2"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION of the BRETHREN, who are for the eſtabliſhed Government and Judicatories of this Church, expreſsing their earneſt deſires of Union and Peace with their Diſſenting Brethren.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may juſtly ſeem ſtrange to all impartiall Obſervers, and cannot but be looked on, by all the lovers of <hi>Zion,</hi> as a ſad and humbling diſpenſation, That after ſo many years toſſing about a debate now ſo far removed out of our way, and after ſo many endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for an accommodation; We ſhould yet be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to expreſſe our ſad reſentment of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of our diſtempers, and of the afflicted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of this Nationall Church. For our part, we have been from the beginning, and yet are, ſo ſenſible of the evill and prejudice of theſe Diviſions, that as we have made Conſcience of lamenting them before the Lord, and afflicting our ſouls becauſe of them, and for the ſins pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing the ſame; So we have not forborn, from time to time, to ſeek peace and purſue it upon any terms that might be conſiſtent with the ſimple freedom of our own judgements in the matters controverted, and with the being of Presbyteriall-government, which we believe to be of God, and which the Lord in mercy hath eſtabliſhed among us in anſwer to the prayers of many, of whom ſome now ſleep in the Lord, and by the no ſmall ſufferings and troubles of the preſent generation. We are nor ſo inſenſible, as men, how we have lien under many diſadvantages in our oppoſing our Brethrens irregular courſes deſtructive to that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nor, as Chriſtians and Miniſters of the Goſpel, how God might juſtly plague any private intereſt or deſigne of ours which ſhould add fewell to that fire; and how our main work hath been retarded and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107207:3"/>obſtructed by theſe contentions, That we ſhould take any pleaſure in them, if ſo be we could obtain peace upon ſafe and juſt terms. In pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance whereof, both in our conferences with our Brethren at home, and of late in <hi>England,</hi> and in our Repreſentation publiſhed to the world, we have expreſſed our earneſt deſires for peace, and our ready condeſcendence to gain them to an Union in the Lord for carrying on the work of God amongſt us; though as yet without any deſired ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe: but while we have been ſeeking peace, ſome of them have been ſailing all winds to compaſſe their own ends and ſet up a domination of their Party in this Church.</p>
            <p>We are ſorry we have ſo much cauſe to complain of our Brethren, that they ſhould not only have begun a needleſſe rent in this Church upon a Queſtion ſo extrinſick to our Doctrine, Worſhip, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; But that ſince they have ſo notably injured us in our Perſons and Miniſtery, by caſting ſo many and ſo foul reproaches upon us, both by word and write at home and abroad, that ſo they might make us hatefull, and purchaſe credite and power to their own Party; whereby alſo they have endeavoured to render this Nationall Church odious in the view of the world, and expoſed her to be a laughing-ſtock to all her enemies on all hands, and furniſhed them with weapons (if their foul ſlanders deſerved to have credite) whereby to fight againſt her, and juſtifie their oppoſition to her, when her own Children bear ſuch witneſſe againſt her. Though we heartily wiſh our Brethren may ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider and lay to heart thoſe their actings; Yet, for our part, we profeſſe it is not our purpoſe to impoſe upon their Judgements in theſe matters of our differences; nor do we keep at a diſtance from them upon the account of any ſuch perſonall injuries, having learned from our Maſter to forgive, and patiently to bear; hoping that as theſe aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are not believed by theſe who know us, ſo in due time He will wipe them off, to the conviction of all who do not wilfully blind their own eyes. But our ſtumbling at our Brethren, is meerly upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the wrongs they have done, and daily do to the ſettled Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Church; from which, if they would once ceaſe, and provide againſt them for the future, our debates with them were at a cloſe.</p>
            <p>As our hopes of peace after our firſt rupture were ſoon blaſted, when we perceived our Brethren not ſiſting at the firſt cauſe of their rent, but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107207:3"/>ſtarting new quarrels to increaſe alienations; So we did eaſily foreſee that their way did manifeſtly tend to the overturning of the eſtabliſhed Church-government; and that, if they did not hearken unto peace, there was no remedy but they behoved to run ſome courſe deſtructive thereunto. We could in prudence judge no otherwiſe, when in the very entry we found them decline the Authority of the Supreme Church-Judicatory in this Nation once and again, and ready to do ſo from time to time at their pleaſure; and drawing Factions and Parties with them in that oppoſition, and branding Church-officers and inferiour Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, as generally corrupt, that ſo all of them might be caſt looſe, or, at leaſt, moulded to their mind. But they did not long leave us to our own conjectures and fears in this matter; having ſoon after, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to this day, by their irregular practices contrary to all order (upon the account of their Declinatour, and the pretended corruption of this Church, both Officers and Members which they could never make out, though often put to it) bewrayed their ſmall reſpect to the eſtabliſhed Government; planting Congregations in a tumultuous and diſorderly way, without reſpect either to the Church Judicatories, or to the juſt intereſt of the People of the Congregation; and counter-acting to the Reſolutions and Determinations of Judicatories, when any of them pleaſed to be diſſatisfied therewith; with many the like practices which we take no pleaſure to repeat. And we found yet more cauſe to judge that theſe were not the deeds only of ſome few amongſt them, more forward and violent than the reſt, but agreeable to the principles of all, at leaſt, of their prime Leaders, when our conference for Union with them, in <hi>November,</hi> 1655. was broken-up chiefly upon this account (beſide ſome other things mentioned in our Repreſentation) That we could not denude the Church-Judicatories of their juſt Power, and devolve matters into the hands of an extra-judiciall Committee of equal numbers, and that they expreſly refuſed ſubordination and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Church Judicatories to which they and we were ſolemnly engaged at our Admiſſion to the Miniſtry, and which we were willing to renew for our parts, and without which our eſtabliſhed Judicatories ſhall be nothing elſe but ſo many conſultative meetings: A principle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with Presbyteriall-government in a conſtituted Church, as all who are acquainted with debates of that nature will eaſily perceive.</p>
            <p>The prejudices to the Church-government flowing from their way,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107207:4"/>did not ſiſt here; we were but too much further confirmed in our juſt grounds of fear, while ſome of them did endeavour to enervate the power of Church-judicatories by procuring an Order putting the power of giving Teſtimonie to Intrants (which is due to Presbyteries only, who are authorized to judge of their Call, and to try and ordain them) in the hands of ſome ſelect perſons of their own chooſing. And when it pleaſed the Lord to break that ſnare, their leading men have again of late attempted the utter ruine of this Church and of theſe who differ from them: Under the pretext of ſeeking a commiſſion for plantation of Churches, they projected to have the power of diſpoſing the legall maintenance of Miniſters put in the hands of that Commiſſion; though they know ſuch a power was never given nor aſſumed by ſuch a Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory, but that it is contrary to the order eſtabliſhed by the Law of the Land; the great deſign thereof being not only to call the Authority of the late Aſſemblies in queſtion as they expreſſe in their deſire, but to have the maintenance put in the hands of men to their mind who were the propoſers of the Overture, that ſo they might diſcourage all who are oppoſite to them from the Miniſtrie: But not contenting themſelves with this, they have further propoſed and projected to have it impoſed upon us, <hi>That there ſhould be a particular Viſitation appointed in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Synod, conſiſting of equal numbers of both Judgements, the one half to be choſen by the one party, and the other by the other party</hi> reſpective, <hi>with power given them from the Synods for purging and planting Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Elders, and compoſing preſent and future Diviſions in Presbyteries and Congregations within the bounds of the Synod; And, that there ſhould be alſo a general Committee of Delegats from the ſeveral Synods, of equal numbers, choſen as aforeſaid, and antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized by Synods, without whoſe previous advice and conſent the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Synods may not reverſe any thing done by the aforeſaid Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and ſuch Viſitation and Committee to continue only till the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent differences be healed, or till the Lord in providence miniſter ſome better way for ſettling peace among use.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe projects we look upon as ſetting up in effect a new Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call juriſdiction, and a plant which is not of Gods planting, and not only ſuſpending the eſtabliſhed Church-government <hi>ſine die,</hi> but totally ſubverting it to make way for the projecters their domination in the Church and over their Brethren. For, this courſe projected by them,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107207:4"/>doth clearly take away the power of Synods and Presbyteries, not only in the matter of our preſent differences, and in the matter of purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and planting Miniſters and Elders (wherein the chief exerciſe of their power conſiſteth) but in all ſuture diviſions: And what may not men affecting preheminence make a matter of difference that they may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue themſelves in power? It laieth alſo for a foundation, an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal imputation upon the Synods and other Church-judicatories as not worthy to be truſted with the Work committed to them by Chriſt; and that they will not be ſo faithful in the Work of Reformation, nor in compoſing any difference which may ariſe hereafter of what importance ſo ever, as theſe Delegates choſen after a new mould. So that a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative is led to lay aſide Synods and Presbyteries when any party pleaſeth to quarrel them, and they muſt lend their power to give ſome ſhaddow of Authority to any Party who pleaſeth to tread upon them. It is a tyrannicall impoſition upon Synods, that they muſt give their power to perſons whom they have not liberty to chooſe, nor power to call them to an account; and muſt ſet up a juriſdiction above them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with, at leaſt, a Negative voice to fruſtrate all their actings, if theſe Delegates pleaſe: Yea, not only is a Negative voice required to be given them in or over all the Judicatories of this Church; (which by parity of reaſon cannot be denied to any Party that pleaſeth to make a rent, if ſo be it be given to our Brethren, who are ſo few in number in compariſon of the body of the Miniſtrie of this Church, and very few or none at all of them being in ſome Synods) But hereby alſo a way is laid for perpetuating differences and contentions, by yoking Parties of equal numbers together in debate, who probably will not cede to other, and ſo in ſtead of compoſing, the breach ſhall be widened. Nor do we ſee here any deſire or purpoſe to put an end to this arbitrary juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, but for any thing we know, it might be perpetual, and the Synods never return to their due liberty if thoſe propoſals once took place: for not only were it in their power to continue preſent differences ſo long as they pleaſe, and conſequently to continue that extra-judicial power to compoſe them, much more if they muſt be continued for compoſing any future diviſions they ſhall be pleaſed to ſtart; But if in proceſſe of time this way ſhall not pleaſe them, they (in ſtead of recurring to Chriſts own inſtitutions) do give us an hint of ſome better way, which they expect may be miniſtred for ſetling peace.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:107207:5"/>
            <p>As we are confident that (upon theſe and many other weighty conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations) all who cordially own the Church-government as of divine right, will be aſhamed of ſuch encroachments; So we heartily wiſh thoſe who have had hand in them, may lay to heart their carriage toward their Mother-church, whoſe intereſts they are bound by the oath of God to maintain. And though we doubt nothing of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied endeavours (if they perſiſt in their former temper) yet again to ſet on foot and proſecute thoſe their purpoſes, and that they may pretend to proſecute them as the only expedient to draw us to Union; which is in effect to caſt all Chriſts intereſts among us under their feet, and to force us to what terms of Union they pleaſe, when they ſhall have us in their power: Yet, for our part, we reſolve, in the power of the Lords Grace, never to accord thereunto, nor recede from the eſtabliſhed Government, be the hazard what it will. But what ever may be the Lords purpoſe to permit men to do to that Government, we will never buy peace at ſo dear a rate as the ruine thereof, nor be acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory thereunto by any deed of ours.</p>
            <p>We have expreſſed our thoughts more fully in theſe things, without any purpoſe to defame or irritate our Brethren, or to charge theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive courſes upon all of them, but meerly for our own vindication and juſtification in our adhering to our principles, in oppoſing theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments, and for our own exoneration before the world, and to our Brethren, if ſo be they will ſeriouſly ponder and weigh the tendency of theſe courſes, and, being wearied of thoſe unpleaſing unprofitable and ſcandalous contentions, they will give proof of their love to peace and to the wel-fare of their Mother-church and Chriſts precious intereſts in her, by thinking upon an aggreement with us in the Lord. And albeit our Brethren may before this time fully know our mind in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, by our conference with them; and we have alſo given an account thereof to the world in our Repreſentation. Yet we do once again hold our ſelves bound to declare our readineſſe to contribute to our outmoſt for advancing ſo good a work; and that, what ever wrongs we have ſuſtained, yet we are heartily content to burie in oblivion all former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, and to be far from any animoſities which might have flowed from the ſame; that ſo we and they may joyntly concur to uphold the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church-government in the conſtitution thereof, and due ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiation and ſubmiſſion thereunto, according to the lawfull known
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107207:5"/>principles wherein we have walked formerly, which both of us have profeſſed to be of Divine right, and the preſervation whereof we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they ought to prefer to any private intereſt whatſoever. And we believe it will afford them more peace in end ſo to do, than if they had obtained all their irregular deſires which they have ſo induſtriouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted. And albeit they differ from us in Judgement upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our firſt difference, yet we judge that needeth be no impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Union; ſeing we have already offered and declared, that though we hold faſt our own Judgement, yet we ſhall not impoſe upon their Judgements in that matter, it being now buried and taken out of our way: But we aggree that the matter be remitted to the determination of a Generall Aſſembly, when the Lord ſhall grant the liberty thereof according to the eſtabliſhed order, to whoſe determination we ſubmit our ſelves. And we ſee not how our Brethren ſhall be able to juſtifie themſelves before the world, or in their own Conſciences, if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a rent ſo prejudiciall, meerly becauſe we cannot renounce our Judgements in ſuch a debate, and ſay as they ſay.</p>
            <p>Whereas it hath been often alleaged againſt us, as a mean of heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tening Diviſions, and an obſtruction to Union, that by ſome Acts of the late Aſſemblies, a barr is laid in the way to keep men who are not of our Judgement from the Miniſtery, and to hold out men of their Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (though never ſo Godly) from being Members of Church-Judicatories. We ſhall not now inſiſt to clear the juſtice and neceſſity of the concluſions of theſe Aſſemblies at that time, and to ſhew that nothing was then done, but what had been done formerly in like caſes: We might alſo inſtruct that (though ſome very few Presbyteries have required of Intrants to the Miniſtery, of whatſoever Judgement, that they ſhould promiſe not to trouble the peace of the Church with theſe needleſſe debates, yet) to our beſt knowledge none of theſe Acts have been <hi>de facto</hi> a barr to hold out any Godly man, who was lawfully and orderly called and tried, though we may but too juſtly complain how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious and active they have been to thruſt-in men of their Judgement, and to cruſh Godly and able men who did not aggree with them. But to free our Brethren from all jealouſies and grounds of ſuſpition, and to juſtifie our ſelves before the world, as to our ſincere and earneſt deſire of Union, we ſhall willingly aggree that all theſe Acts be made void and null by the next General Aſſembly, to whom it belongeth to repeal Acts;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107207:6"/>and that in the mean time they ſhall not be put in practice. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they make ſo great a noiſe of the Cenſures inflicted on ſome of their number by the Aſſembly, 1651. Though we might ſay much on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Aſſembly their proceeding at that time, and of their lenitie who did Cenſure only four of their number, who yet have never ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto theſe Cenſures, and conſequently have the leſſe cauſe to complain: Yet to aſſure them that we are reall for peace, and do not minde nor deſire the perſonall prejudice of any of them, but only the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the order of this afflicted Church; we are content that the Synods (ſince a Generall Aſſembly doth not meet) do take off the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that are upon their reſpective Members; they giving aſſurance of their ſubmiſſion and ſubordination to the Judicatories, without which there can be no order nor Government, and which we have to this day conſtantly obſerved in our practice, and they alſo with us untill the times of our late differences.</p>
            <p>And whereas our Brethren affirm, that their chief aim and ſcope in all their late actings, hath been to find out ſome effectuall way for purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of ſcandalous and inſufficient Miniſters, and other Officers; We might too juſtly complain that this is but a Queſtion ſtarted on the by, and ſince the time they had begun a rupture amongſt us, And that they have ſo liberally aſperſed the Miniſtry of this Church who differ from them, both at home and abroad, when yet upon exacteſt trialls, both by them and us, nothing can be found anſwerable to the great cry raiſed againſt this Church and our Miniſtery. Yet in this buſſineſſe, we ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly declare we do not contravert with them, having profeſſed our willingneſſe to go about that work in the moſt ſtrict way, according to juſtice and the common rules of Church-Judicatories in ſuch caſes: And we have not only often intreated them to unite upon this very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that the work of purging might be carried on more effectually; but have upon all occaſions of any report of ſcandall or inſufficiency, laid forth our ſelves to the utmoſt to try and examine the truth thereof, and have not been wanting in inflicting due Cenſure for any thing that at any time was found. Yea, ſo far are we from fore-ſlowing or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing, that to declare our readineſſe and ſincerity in that matter, we are content, if our Brethren be not ſatisfied with the rules of procedure hitherto aggreed upon, that they condeſcend upon the ſtricteſt rules can be deſired in juſtice for triall and cenſure; and we ſhall be willing to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107207:6"/>obſerve them, providing they be rules binding for all, and to which all will ſubmit, both they and we.</p>
            <p>Having thus again expreſſed our ſelves in this matter, we do ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in the bowels of Jeſus Chriſt, Exhort and Obteſt all our Brethren, that as they do tender the Government of this Church, and the welfare of Chriſts Intereſts therein, they would lay aſide prejudices and animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and ceaſe from all irregular practices, and all things tending to hold up diviſions and widen the breach: And that now at laſt, after ſo many experiences of the bitter fruits of contention, they will joyn cordially to uphold the Lords Intereſts, and go on in His Work; that ſo the Goſpel, and work of Reformation may proſper amongſt us, the Lord may take delight to continue His habitation in the midſt of us, and ſtumbling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blocks may be removed out of the way of the People, which have been multiplied by theſe differences. We have made choice of this way of making known our inclinations to peace, not upon any ſiniſter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, but meerly that our heart in this matter may be made known to all our Brethren and the Lords People in the Land, and that our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſions may not be huddled up in a conference with ſome few, who may keep them up, or repreſent them to others as they pleaſe; but that all knowing our minde, there may be a foundation laid for begetting a good underſtanding, and making up an Union with all theſe whom the Lord ſhall convince of the neceſſity of peace in this poor Church, which we deſire may be ſpeedily gone about, conſidering the ſad prejudices following upon this rupture, and the ſo long continuance thereof. And we cannot in reaſon but expect that our Brethren will hearken to our ſerious requeſt, if ſo be they be real in their profeſſions for Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial-government, and do mind only the advancement of the work of God amongſt us, and be not driving ſome other deſign all this while. But if after all theſe eſſayes and deſires of Union, we be ſtill, to our great grief, fruſtrated of our intentions, and men will continue an unneceſſary Schiſm in the Church, Though we ſhall deſire to reverence and ſtoup to the Lords holy diſpenſation in it, and (as hitherto we have done) ſhall look upon that ſad and humbling lot (more grievous to us than any thing could be fall us in our particular concernments) as a call from Him exciting us to our work, that we may lay forth our ſelves in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, to make our Maſter Chriſt more known to His people, and bring-in Diſciples to Him, and may make full proof of our Miniſtrie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107207:7"/>In all the parts and opportunities thereof, that our Lord when He cometh may find us ſo doing; Yet, as to thoſe who perſiſt in ſuch courſes, we muſt ſay that we have exonered our ſelves, in diſcharge of our duty towards them, and we hope it will appear to all unbyaſſed Diſcerners, that, notwithſtanding all their violent attempts againſt the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government and us, ſince our conference with them, yet we are not at all irritated thereby to recede from the condeſcenſions and offers then made. And as we do commit Chriſts Intereſts into His own hand, that He may ſee to the preſervation thereof, againſt thoſe uſurpations and encroachments of men, and ſhall deſire to lament after Him, till He be pleaſed to diſpell thoſe clouds and ſhine upon this diſtracted Church; So we invite all the Lords People in the Land that they will not give place to Satans craft in theſe times who would take them off the main work of Godlineſſe and Religion, and engage them in fruitleſſe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and debates, whereof they will have neither profit nor pleaſure in end; But that with us they will lay to heart and lament all the evils that have come and do daily grow upon us by theſe ſad Diviſions, and that in their Stations they will adhere to the Intereſts of Chriſt, and the ſettled Government of His Church, not ſuffering themſelves to be miſled by the ſpecious pretexts of men while they run courſes ſo deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive thereunto; As conſidering that it will be no grief of heart to them in the latter end, when the Lord will judge, not according to appearances or pretext, but righteous judgement, that they have had no acceſſion to the ruine of their Mother-Church, but have been a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to her in the day of her diſtreſſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:107207:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
